<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Your awesome title</title>
    <description>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.
</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 06:57:01 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 06:57:01 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.3.4</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Card networks 101: What do Visa and Mastercard do?</title>
        <description>&lt;script src=&quot;https://unpkg.com/mermaid@11.12.0/dist/mermaid.min.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people can recognize the Visa and Mastercard brands. If you do, chances are you use one of their cards to transact every day. You may have some notion that most places (in the US) take both, but some places only take Visa (e.g. Costco), and vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what do they do? &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lnz2gRPDzrA&quot;&gt;Here’s Visa’s attempt&lt;/a&gt; to answer that question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few things they don’t do&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:dont-do&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:dont-do&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They aren’t the company that provides the card. Nor are they a bank, though the card you have is probably issued by one (Chase, Capital One, BofA, etc). These are called &lt;strong&gt;“card issuers”&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They don’t distribute point of sale methods or online checkouts, which are done by &lt;strong&gt;payment processors&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They aren’t responsible for onboarding or underwriting stores and merchants. That is typically done by payment processors and banks, called &lt;strong&gt;“merchant acquirers”&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They don’t manufacture or print cards.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nor do they manufacture the point of sale hardware.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, Visa and Mastercard are &lt;strong&gt;card networks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:card-network-name&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:card-network-name&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, facilitating card transactions by connecting the cardholders and issuers to the merchants and acquirers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This forms a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Two-sided_market&quot;&gt;two-sided market&lt;/a&gt; of all the participants in a transaction&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:or-four&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:or-four&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;mermaid&quot;&gt;
---
config:
  theme: &apos;neutral&apos;
  fontFamily: system-ui, -apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, &apos;Segoe UI&apos;, Roboto, Oxygen, Ubuntu, Cantarell, &apos;Open Sans&apos;, &apos;Helvetica Neue&apos;, sans-serif;
  nodeSpacing: 20
  rankSpacing: 20
  flowchart: 
    subGraphTitleMargin: {bottom: 20}
---
%% For some reason arrows are still showing up in the Obsidian preview, but not in Mermaid online editor
flowchart LR
    subgraph Issuing[**Issuing**]
        direction TB
        CI[Card issuer] --- CH[Cardholder]
    end
    subgraph Acquiring[**Acquiring**]
        direction TB
        MA[Merchant acquirer] --- M[Merchant]
    end
    Issuing ---- CN[**Card network**]
    CN ---- Acquiring
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The key players in a card transaction.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The card network’s job is to enable card transactions, and also to spread the use of their card brands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This boils down to four key responsibilities:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Run the physical network infrastructure to route transactions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Coordinate the banking network to settle transactions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set the incentives to encourage the use of the network.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set and enforce rules of the network, including a mechanism for disputes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the rest of the discussion, we’ll focus on Visa for simplicity, as it’s what I’m most familiar with, although Mastercard operates in more or less the same ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;1-run-the-physical-infrastructure&quot;&gt;1. Run the physical infrastructure&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we talk about networks in the context of telecommunications, we think of the Internet, a network of computers connected together by fiber and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.submarinecablemap.com/&quot;&gt;deep sea cables&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, card networks are no different, but predate the Internet (although now part of it): they maintain massive data centers and lease physical cables to connect issuers and acquirers electronically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The card network role’s in a transaction is &lt;em&gt;routing&lt;/em&gt;. Similar to IP addresses,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:pan-exhaustion&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:pan-exhaustion&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; card numbers, also known as Primary Account Numbers (PANs) are used to route requests from the merchant’s checkout to the issuing bank, where the transaction gets checked then approved or declined. The first 6 to 8 digits of the PAN is called a Bank Identification Number, or BIN, and identifies the issuing bank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- TODO: support sidenotes/asides https://kau.sh/blog/jekyll-footnote-tufte-sidenote/ --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visa takes its data centers very seriously. They are highly secure, redundant, and fitted to survive all kinds of disasters. From &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.networkcomputing.com/data-center-networking/inside-visa-s-data-center&quot;&gt;Inside Visa’s Data Center (Network Computing, 2013)&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The company’s flagship data center, dubbed Operations Center East, or OCE, is a 140,000-square-foot facility that Visa will only say is located “somewhere along the Eastern seaboard.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Not surprisingly, the facility, which is also designed to withstand earthquakes and gale-force winds up to 170 miles per hour, is locked down like a digital Fort Knox. The roads entering the complex have hydraulic bollards that can shoot up fast enough to stop a vehicle traveling up to 50 miles per hour dead in its tracks. (The road is too curvy to drive safely at higher speeds.) Visitors must pass through a security gate, be cleared by roving security teams, and then be subjected to a biometric scan before being admitted.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20120330102616/https://www.usatoday.com/tech/news/story/2012-03-25/visa-data-center/53774904/1/&quot;&gt;Another article&lt;/a&gt; claims Visa’s OCE is guarded by a a moat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That top secret location? In &lt;a href=&quot;https://maps.app.goo.gl/tPEDWcTiY621sZz37&quot;&gt;Ashburn, Virginia&lt;/a&gt;, conveniently located by Trader Joe’s and Topgolf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;!-- From https://stackoverflow.com/a/19360305/7971276 --&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
&lt;!-- Need to | escape the description so I can include quotation marks --&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2025/visa-oce-satellite.png&quot; alt=&quot;I think the &amp;quot;moat&amp;quot; is the pool of water on the top center-left.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;I think the &quot;moat&quot; is the pool of water on the top center-left.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;2-run-the-banking-network&quot;&gt;2. Run the banking network&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;3-set-incentives&quot;&gt;3. Set incentives&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;4-set-rules-and-handle-disputes&quot;&gt;4. Set rules and handle disputes&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More cards → more merchants. More merchants → more cards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In another article, they claim to have &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20120330102616/https://www.usatoday.com/tech/news/story/2012-03-25/visa-data-center/53774904/1/&quot;&gt;a moat&lt;/a&gt; protecting the data center.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Inside the pods, 376 servers, 277 switches, 85 routers and 42 firewalls–all connected by 3,000 miles of cable–hum around the clock, enabling transactions around the globe in near real-time and keeping Visa’s business running.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Inside the pods, 376 servers, 277 switches, 85 routers and 42 firewalls–all connected by 3,000 miles of cable–hum around the clock, enabling transactions around the globe in near real-time and keeping Visa’s business running.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20120330102616/https://www.usatoday.com/tech/news/story/2012-03-25/visa-data-center/53774904/1/&quot;&gt;Top secret Visa data center banks on security, even has moat (USA Today, 2013)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;the crux of their operation is an electronic one, and&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:dont-do&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Nowadays they may have product offerings for some of these, or own subsidiaries that do some of these, but these are not core to the business of being a card network. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:dont-do&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:card-network-name&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;To be precise, they are the companies running the card networks. Colloquially, we call them the card networks. For example, VisaNet is technically the card network, Visa is the company/brand. Mastercard’s is called Banknet. They both own and operate subsidiary networks, such as specialized debit and ATM networks, like Visa’s Interlink and Plus, or Mastercard’s Cirrus and Maestro, although technically VisaNet and Banknet can process debit (this is a story for another time). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:card-network-name&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:or-four&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Or four, depending on how you count. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:or-four&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:pan-exhaustion&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Similar to IPv4, 16 digit PANs are rapidly exhausting due to the use of anonymized “token” PANs used by things like Apple/Google Pay and saved payment details. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:pan-exhaustion&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/posts/2025/10/02/card-networks.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/posts/2025/10/02/card-networks.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Money, banking, and payments: a constructivist approach.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Not too long ago, my perception of money was cash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my view, if you went to a bank and deposited a dollar, at the end of the day, the dollar would be placed neatly next to a stack of gold bricks, in a vault deep beneath the bank. In this imagining, if you sent a wire, the dollar (or another like it) would be aboard an armored car to the other bank, or a armored plane if you paid more for same day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This mostly wrong. But I suspect the banking and payments, and money generally, are a mystery to most people. Like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What does Visa do? What does Mastercard do? Why are they different?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Or: How does a dollar get around, if not by armored car?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Or even: Wait, you’re telling me there’s no vault of gold bricks?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To answer these questions, and more, I invite the reader to close their eyes and imagine a time before money, to see how we can invent these systems from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are &lt;a href=&quot;https://monoskop.org/images/9/96/Le_Guin_Ursula_K_1986_1989_The_Carrier_Bag_Theory_of_Fiction.pdf&quot;&gt;Boog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have recently invented Agriculture. On paper (not yet invented), settling down near your food is a devious scheme, but you were far busier than expected and eating oats all day &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neolithic_Revolution#Diet_and_health&quot;&gt;has not felt great&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, you go to Grob, your hunter buddy, to get some wooly mammoth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“For Rock-god’s sake!” cries Grob. “This is the sixth time this rock-week. What’s in it for me?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so, you agree to exchange 3 bowls of oatmeal for a delicious mammoth-steak, and thus Commerce is born (Altruism begins its endless demise).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things are going well. Your oat fields grow large and bounteous. Others settle down near you for oats, and you exchange oats for Goods and Services. Eventually, enough people settle down, inventing Civilization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Problems quickly emerge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are sick and tired of oats. You are happy to trade vast sums of oats for modern indulgences like Clothing, Bronze, and Stone Tablets. But oats have become so commonplace that the oat-rate for these luxuries has reached the hundreds of bushels (this is called Inflation). This is too much for you to carry around, and far too many oats for anyone to eat at once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You devise another devious schemes: instead of exchanging oats directly, you write down how many oats you owe to who in a ledger. This way people can redeem their oats in smaller quantities, and you don’t need to carry anything around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The system is pretty good. So good, that people start coming to you to ask you to move their numerical-oats from their oat-account to another when trading with others. It works so well that everything is priced in oats, even as fewer and fewer people are redeeming their numerical-oats for physical-oats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is called the “Money of Account”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make this easier so you don’t need to be involved in every transaction, you design an oat-redemption-token made of pocketable circles of Bronze. “This is a COIN – Contains Oats In Numbers,” you say, holding up a Bronze circle. “You can use this as a Unit of Exchange. Now please stop bothering me.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is called “Cash”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, we’ve been having too much fun here. Let’s break down what we’ve uncovered:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Money can be a number, like the “money of account”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Money can be a thing, like cash, or oats.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in fact, a number is much more portable than a thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Next time: banks.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/posts/2025/08/28/money.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/posts/2025/08/28/money.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
